"Low Protein Diets
for Parkinson's Disease"
Parkinson's disease is a disease
of dopamine deficiency in the brain.
You can't just have people take
dopamine because it can't
pass through the blood-brain barrier,
but you can give people
a dopamine precursor
called levodopa, or L-dopa,
which can get up into the brain
and be turned into dopamine.
However, with prolonged treatment,
patients start to show a reduced
response to levodopa. After
5 years of levodopa treatment,
the benefits start wearing
off before the next dose,
or don't completely contain symptoms
in a substantial proportion of patients,
and represents a major source
of disability, and significantly
impairs quality of life. Therefore,
maximizing the therapeutic efficiency
of levodopa is an important
goal, and that's where
protein-restricted diets come in.
Wait, what does protein
have to do with Parkinson's?
Certain amino acids in proteins
have been proven to impair
the therapeutic effect of levodopa
by reducing its absorption
and influx into the brain,
because they use
the same transporter so
can crowd each other out.
Here's a before-and-after PET
scan showing levodopa activity
in the brain before and
after protein loading.
That's why protein-restricted diets
can improve the efficacy of levodopa.
There are three ways to do that:
an overall low-protein diet,
a so-called protein-redistribution
diet, or a combination of the two.
As a dietary strategy,
a low-protein diet is nice because
it's not only effective, but also
simple to understand and follow.
And by low protein, we're just talking
about sticking to the recommended
amount of protein, 0.8 grams
per kilogram of body weight.
As I've covered before, most people
are eating excess protein
and suffering because of it.
0.8 grams per KG is equivalent
to about 0.36 grams per pound.
So you take your weight in
pounds, multiply times 0.36,
and get how many grams in
protein you should eat in a day.
So if you weigh 140 pounds,
you should eat about 50
grams of protein a day.
The positive effect of limiting dietary
protein can be noticed within
one week, even in patients no longer
responding to the manipulation
of levodopa's medication schedule
or to other anti-Parkinson drugs.
Protein-redistribution diets have
been investigated most thoroughly,
and have been confirmed
to be effective with a remarkable
60 to 100% response rate.
We know about the deleterious
influence of dietary protein
and the benefit of a low-protein
diet; however, it's not only
the total amount of daily protein
but also how it's distributed
over the day. If we eat only
protein-rich foods at night,
staying under a total of 10 grams
a day for breakfast and lunch,
then we eliminate the amino
acid surges during the day,
and who cares if they surge
after we go to bed?
Parkinson's is a movement
disorder, and so if the drugs
are not going to work,
then it might as well be
when you're sleeping.
Fiber is another way to
get levodopa to work better.
Significant improvements
in L-dopa blood levels and
Parkinson's symptoms starting
as early as 30 to 60 minutes
after eating a diet rich
in insoluble fiber, like the kind
found concentrated in whole grains.
Well, if fiber helps, then how
about a plant-based diet
for the management
of Parkinson's disease?
You don't know until
you put it to the test.
They looked at a normal protein
amount redistributed plant-based diet,
and Parkinson's patients saw a
significant improvement in symptoms
and performance, making it
a convenient way to conjugate
the positive effects of
non-excess protein intake
and a high fiber intake without
limiting total food amount.
Planning such a diet is rather simple,
centering around unprocessed
plant foods, but reserving protein-rich
plants like beans, split peas,
chickpeas, lentils, and
peanuts to the evening meal.
And voila --- the clinical improvement
hit all the major motor signs:
the rigidity, the tremor, and
slowness of movement,
the things that really matter
to Parkinson's patients,
in particular the tremor, the shaking,
which often does not respond
to drugs but was highly positively
affected by the plant-based diet.
So plants may be preferable
for Parkinson's,
but you don't know how well it will
work for you until you give it a try.